there's a question a a friend raised a
few days ago and
and
it's quite common
that once you start
becoming steady in your
practice the base the the
basic practice of virtue sense restraint
when you're doing that for you know a
good year or so
and things are maybe you've got a lot of
energy for practice and contemplation
but then it just
quietens out hmm
there is no more like questions in a way
you're not necessarily free you're not
free from suffering
you suffer but you you're now in a very
comfortable Zone
yeah yeah because well you're not
breaking any precepts yeah you're you're
comfortable in Center strains you can't
yeah well that's that's basically then
the time the Buddha says in the suit is
when you have to kind of arouse energy
for things that are not yet attained
because as we said so many times precepts in
as we said so many times precepts in
themselves
will not lead will not guarantee
understanding precepts are necessary for
understanding but
but
in themselves they will not lead to
understanding if you don't make the
effort to understand what needs to be
understood so although they are not optional in
so although they are not optional in
themselves they are not sufficient
so if somebody has been you know keep
living according to the precepts sense
restraint and so on great but now you
actually have to make the further effort
it's not like oh what what now
um so that doesn't change the lifestyle
of precepts doesn't change but on top of
that you have to start you know
Rising a bit of sense of
urgency reflecting about things you are liable
reflecting about things you are liable
making a point out of it
um and then yeah maybe perhaps if if the
environment is too familiar too
comfortable to something you're very accustomed to
to something you're very accustomed to
changing up a bit experience fatigue
elements lack of sleep and see how much
of your
a steady practice remains and how much
of it sort of starts to
be challenged because you're going to
see that even the person is bothered by
it might be bothered by things being now
too calm there's well yes and it's hard
like it's hard to it might be hard for
somebody to to kind of bring up that
energy and determination to to think
about things not to entertain and things
you're liable when nothing's directly
sort of pressuring you're poking you
know things have been calmed relatively
your environment has been studied
controlled you live remotely nothing
coming up oh it's fine I'm content but
yeah like there is more to be done
obviously so that's that's like when you
want to just not necessarily destroy
your house and and lean burn it and
leave and just just you know
become a homeless person to experience
the change but just go somewhere for a
while somewhere different where you're
not in control where you're like you
know you might have to put up with such
elements um that's when we like go to Forest go
um that's when we like go to Forest go
hiking go some go stay stay away in a
less comfortable environment because go
visit some family
I suppose yeah but I'm still trying to
keep it along the you know practice of
sense restraint
yeah go to go to people who that's like
again that's only because only if you
cannot yourself sustain
uh those Reflections there would be a
rising sense of urgency and to to
practice towards things you haven't yet
attained like if you can't though you're
just trying the mind just drifts away
then okay yeah change it up a bit like
you know or even within the setting that
you have don't eat for a day or two
get up earlier than you would usually
just to sort of you know prod the lazy
body and the mind experience a bit of
discomfort and then you'll see okay it's
right there things that I need to deal
with they're not abstract they are not
hidden in some like you know distant
parts of my reflection that I have to
spend days of traveling before I arrive
at what I need to do you know just a bit
of lack of sleep not enough food a bit
of fatigue and see how much you remain
mindful after all of that
getting getting your views challenged
that too exactly sure yeah yeah but then
you need to find people who would
challenge users I mean relatives could
you know like people who were trying to
yeah have your views challenged in a
beneficial sense it's not just in
argumentative mind even then for
somebody might be enough to like hey
okay yeah I guess you know maybe I'm not
clear as I thought I was yeah
but yeah to find people who would too
yeah in other words it won't be that
hard to find work to do internally
as long as you know that you need to
find work to do if you start looking you
will find it if some sometimes people
don't think they should look then they
won't find it so
one of the things is once you've become
calm like that and you can't see any
work the hindrances are kind of
already coming up
okay some people would say when I bring
up the hindrances now huh contemplate
things that would make you lustful so
that you would get to deal with the lust
hmm but then so you so you would see okay
but then so you so you would see okay
now I am lustful okay let me understand
it yeah yeah I can see
like the idea behind it
is beneficial
but uh
it would be overshooting it overshooting
the mark so like if somebody doesn't you
know he's not even aware
that there is the last diversion in the
mind and so on you know if you tell them
in a coarse manner well bring up the
last reversion and that's your work you
could see practical benefit of it
however you shouldn't really go all the
way of bring up the lust
or or bring up the aversion all you need
to do is just think about that if I
think about such things lust will arise
and stop there that's enough you don't
need to actually excite yourself or wind
yourself up in order to do it
because just a prospect of being able to
do it and that probably will become
apparent as soon as you start thinking
about doing it
if you start thinking about winding
yourself up you are already if there is
a possibility of you to be wound up you
are already being wound up just by that
possibility so you need to start
recognizing that because it will be much
less efficient and much you would waste
much more effort than if you actually
have to fully excite yourself towards
Central desire and then deal with it or
fully kind of wind yourself up with
anger and aversion and then deal with it
there is no no need to go all the way in
even on the level of the mind sorry but
yes if you are complacent if you don't
know what you're supposed to do yeah
just well can blast the rise in my mind
and you know already you will have an
answer if I were to think such and such
things I will become lost that's it you
don't need to experience the last to
recognize that the last is there and
same if I recall things that were
upsetting for me
and you start a little bit before and
you see okay I will get upset okay stop
there that's enough that that
recognition is sufficient
but definitely it's important to qualify
where the line is because if you don't
qualify it somebody can think that they
must go all the way up until mind is
wound up with anger in order to deal
with it and that's too far
then you will not deal with it up until
anger subsides first then you can deal
with it but if you know when to stop
such as yes think about something that
makes you angry and as you recognize
that you're gonna get angry if you
continue thinking stop
so that's why you shouldn't like arise
hindrances but you should definitely
contemplate about liability to
hindrances so you can say well I'm liable to
so you can say well I'm liable to
getting unliable to suffering on account
of some loss yes take this specific
example then exactly so I lose somebody
or you haven't lost but start thinking
about losing somebody immediately like
if you start going that direction if you
are liable yeah you're going to start
feeling it and you don't have to now
okay but I must go through all this
whole kind of process of winding myself
up
building up all this passion and
aversion to deal with it no no you're
already sufficiently wound up
but so on one hand it's important to
take something specific that could
prompt last or aversion or fear or
anxiety in you and the reason why it's
important actually to have something
specific is so you don't remain in there
on that like abstract plane of yes I am
liable to loss yeah what is loss yeah
you know some people can operate in
those categories mentally but
practically speaking no no find
something that would affect you if you
lose it think about it up until you
start recognizing okay I'm gonna get
wound up and that's when you practice
okay so now I'll stop and this is my
work the possibility of being wound up means
the possibility of being wound up means
I am already wound up
and that's what needs to be endured and
seen on its own for what it is so you
see the danger you're in the
possibilities of well okay
and then you have to question yourself
why am I
why would I suffer if such if I such and
such happen I lose my health no you know
you can imagine
something else yeah losing your teeth or
something sure
yep like you can you can you can you can
explain why you would suffer physically
yeah but why would you mentally be
destroyed on account of such an idea
and another reason why it's important to
not go all the way until like and become
completely wound up or lustful or angry
is because then everything you do
afterwards will be to get rid of the
luster angle not to understand it to get
rid of the pain of it but if you stop
short of being wound up face the
direction of being what possibility of
being wound up think about specific
things that could wind you up but before
you get wound up you stop then thinking
about it will not be as rooted in trying
to manage the pain and get rid of it but
it will actually be on the level of okay
so I'm not quite wound up but I could be
wound up and that's the middle ground
where practice applies
you know I am liable to suffering as the
Buddha would say
we have to ask why why am I well if
you're now on that level then exactly so
why
does that exist like why would that be
affected you can start asking that but
really it's like why would I be bothered
if I'm affected why is that not
acceptable to me okay so if this occurs
and there is the emotional response to
it why is that not why am I resisting
the idea of that why am I defending
myself against it and so on because
right now that possibility is
uncomfortable exactly so why am I then
can I then not
seek this Comfort intentionally but can
I also not intentionally and habitually
and automatically deny it and resist it
and try to get rid of it
can I just endure this Comfort on that
level of
could be wound up but not wound up can I
just stay there and endure it on that
level without being wound up and then
making all the effort to manage it and
get rid of it and think I dealt with it
can I just endure it on this level and
learn how to stop resisting internally
because that height weighs on you
through your resistance of it you stop
resisting it it's just the thing that
endures there
but that endurance as I say so many
times needs to be endured on the right
level which is the level of that
I am about to be wound up or I could be
wound up and experience aversion lasting
Sun but I'm not quite so I'm stopping in
other words I'm restraining my thinking
and you know senses are not engaging
further but at the same time I'm not
denying the direction of you know where
my mind's heading
so Can I Endure things on that level on
that more ambiguous level on that level
that's much easier to doubt and
overwhelm you
because if you're not lustful then your
last full then you apply the practice to
get rid of the last done clear cut
simple ABC you're not angry then you're
angry then you do this when you're angry
simple ABC
but none of that is where the dhamma is
you don't want to be managing those
states of mind because they're painful
you want to be not resisting their pain
so that they don't affect you to begin
with
so the possibility that I could suffer
is suffering yeah
that's already uncomfortable if you if
you discern it that will be felt
uncomfortably so now yeah so now I don't have to go
so now yeah so now I don't have to go
wind myself up because that's it it's
already there but I need something more
palpable no that's your problem that's
the lack of discernment and lack of Mind
development when you think you need
something more palpable and the only
reason you need something more palpable
is because you keep seeking something
more palpable yeah what is palpable is
right exactly because this is possible
enough sufficiently poppable you
recognize it you discern it you see it
but yeah it had ambiguity in itself it's
it's uncomfortable so by seeking
something more palpable but sure in
reality doing is trying to get rid of
discomfort or something
more doubtful less palpable less clear
less less definable
and that's already the form of craving
because I said even like you know big
youth State of Mind State of Mind mind
effective without for example it's real
as such
it's not clear lack of clarity confusion
is this so This that experience as a
whole is real as such and that cannot be
daunted but you need to endure it
sufficiently on that level of that doubt
and ambiguity to recognize it on its own
because now whenever such experience
manifests when you are sort of
experiencing it
the habitual action is go towards
definition Clarity answers not because
you recognize the value of the answer
but because through answering or through
seeking the answer you get rid of the
pain or the discomfort of the doubt
so
I'm comfortable in my practice
but I want to practice I do want to
practice Yeah so let me so what do you
do practice yeah exactly and they're not
watch I wind myself or try to study or
get some get some thoughts going yeah
but that's all because I'm actually
stepping away from practice but it I
think I said in other talks like if
sometimes you know a person reaches that
a bit of a kind of
status quo call
like oh it's all right but I don't see
any further what to do just tighten your
sense restraint
just okay start saying no a bit more two
more things and you'll see immediately
the Mind very short very very uh it
won't be before long mine starts you
know coming up with irrational things
and mind States and moods and so on and
there's your practice now deal with that
go and stay in the forest go hike skip a
meal do something like they would
disturb that that wholesome routine but
would tighten the pressure a bit and if
nothing comes up great tighten it a bit
more nothing comes up well maybe you
really finished all the work but I'm
pretty sure things will come up as soon
as you start tightening
yeah as you say skip a meal you don't
have to go because when we speak often
about you know knowing your intentions
you realize yes you keep the precepts
you live a wholesome life date from the
morning till the evening
but within that if you look at your
intentions closely there will be things
you do out of distraction again not kind
of seriously unwholesome Central desire
or real will and anger but now we're
looking for like a more refined things
to refine blemishes and there will be
things you do out of Desire out of
irritation out of distraction not on
that big scale as I said but still in
its own it's still the same phenomenon
of Desire of ill will and that's your
work so restrain that then
that's all you know restrained by the
body speech and then the Mind thoughts
intentions actions by their mind you
start restraining that in the same sense
your restraining uh physical actions of
you know doing things with the body and
saying things with the map
yeah fear fear that you haven't got it
all worked out so then you everything's
calm but you can have this fear of I
need to have it all worked out you know
my ideas and that's again it would be
rooted in that same thing exactly the
thing I said
I need to have things worked out because
things not worked out is too ambiguous
and uncomfortable to me
thus I want to manage that phenomenon
that discomfort
how can you be sure
that you won't disintegrate
does it make is it a
like how would I know now that I won't
suffer
if all that happens
well but as we said in the beginning
come up with specific things that
because you used to make you suffer that
are making you suffer if that doesn't
work increase the sense restraint just
see what mine will do it's going to
start kicking and screaming
because you tighten its harness
then be patient don't slide back as in
don't go back to centrality and so on
and you wouldn't if nothing is prompting
you you wouldn't have a reason to go
back and then be patient for a while and see
and then be patient for a while and see
if something comes up unforeseen
um keeping the precepts of practicing
sense that's why arahants even
themselves remain Mindful and sense
restraint because they prefer now that
and that's why often you had like even
like anagamis who thought today they
couldn't see anything else to be done
factually they couldn't see anything
else to be done but as Buddha said there
might have been something some subtle
rise in almost like virtually invisible
residue so they remain alert but they
remain alert exactly so we have nothing
to lose either way if you remain alert
sent to strength keeping the presets and
it's also preferred mode of being
there's no end to that yeah that's once
you take up that yeah practice yeah
that's it
so if if none of those things has brings
up any issues or killations or stuff to
deal with fine
now you have completed your work as the
word would say and you would just
continue abiding Mindful and sense
restraint because that's a pleasant mode
of being alive more or less unpleasant
mode of being alive less than Pleasant
mode of enduring the body and the five
Aggregates until they break apart